Finding Aid for Observatory (University of Michigan) records, 1855-1985
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Observatory (University of Michigan) records 1855-1985
University of Michigan. Observatory.
87299 BImu Bimu C455 2
Records of astronomical observatories operated by the University of Michigan including the Detroit Observatory on the Ann Arbor campus (1855-), the Lamont-Hussey Observatory (Bloemfontein, South Africa, 1928-), the McMath-Hulbert Observatory (Portage Lake, Michigan, 1935-1979), the Portage Lake/Peach Mountain Observatory (Dexter, Michigan, 1948-. Records include correspondence files, administrative files, observation notebooks, photographs and architectural drawings.
18 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
350 architectural drawings
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records (donor #s 1278 ), 1465, 4765 ) were transferred in several accessions.
The record group is open to research.
The University of Michigan observatories and the Department of Astronomy have their roots in the university presidency of Henry Tappan. Following his inaugural speech in 1852, Tappan was approached by Henry N. Walker, a Detroit resident wishing to become active in university affairs. Tappan encouraged him to raise funds towards the financing of an astronomical observatory. Walker solicited funds from Detroit citizens and in a few months raised $7,000, an amount more than doubled by further subscriptions.
In 1853, Tappan left for Europe to study various educational systems and to procure instruments for the observatory. While in Prussia, Tappan met Franz Brunnow and offered him the directorship of the university's new observatory. Brunnow became the first director of the observatory and a professor of astronomy at the university, remaining until 1863. Brunnow offered the first systematic course in practical astronomy in the world and the new department was one of the first at the University of Michigan to offer graduate level courses.
The observatory building was completed in the summer of 1854, and the instruments were mounted the following winter. A meridian circle was constructed in Berlin and a twelve-inch refracting telescope, at that time the third largest in the world, was constructed by Henry Fritz of New York. President Tappan named the new observatory in honor of the Detroit residents who contributed much of the funding. In 1931 it was renamed the University of Michigan Observatory.
Professor William J. Hussey was made director of the Observatory in 1904 and began work to enlarge and improve it. Observatory equipment had slowly become outclassed by equipment in use elsewhere. Hussey traveled to South Africa in 1923 to select the ideal location for an observatory to map the southern skies. The impetus for this observatory was Robert P. Lamont's gift of a 27-inch refracting telescope in 1910. The Lamont-Hussey Observatory, consisting of a circular telescope room, fifty-six feet in diameter, was dedicated in April 1928 near Bloemfontein, South Africa.
In 1926, Ralph A. Curtiss became chairman of the Department of Astronomy and director of the Observatory. By 1930, the expansion of Ann Arbor created an environment not conducive to astronomical observation. City and university buildings limited the observatory's horizon, smoke and city lights hampered observation, and heavy trains frequently passed within a few hundred yards and jarred sensitive instruments. Additional observatories would be constructed to maintain the quality of the university's research in astronomy.
The McMath-Hulbert Observatory was presented to the university in 1931 by three donors, Francis and Robert McMath and Judge Henry Hulbert. A grant of $20,000 from the Rackham fund, another from the McGregor Fund and private contributions made it possible in 1935 to build a solar tower telescope. This new telescope brought certain suspected phenomena into clear view and disproved a theory about light-pressure advanced in England. For simultaneous recording, a second tower and telescope were constructed. Robert McMath designed all the instruments and buildings. The University of Michigan discontinued its support of the McMath-Hulbert observatory at the end of June 1979.
The university closed its observatory in South Africa upon the retirement of Director Richard A. Rossiter in 1953, bringing the lens and optical equipment back to Michigan. The Department of Astronomy turned to the development of a radio telescope on Peach Mountain near Portage Lake, Michigan, in conjunction with the Office of Naval Research. The Peach Mountain Observatory was begun in 1948, the result of a grant from the McGregor Fund and the university.
The University of Michigan-Dartmouth College-MIT Astronomy Consortium was officially established in 1975, leading to the establishment of the MDM (Michigan-Dartmouth-MIT) Observatory located on Kitt Peak, 50 miles west of Tucson, Arizona, and 6,300 feet above sea level.
Today, the University of Michigan observatories consist of three different sites, operating a total of four major telescopes. These include a 26 meter telescope at a radio observatory located near Ann Arbor, a .6 meter Curtis Schmidt telescope at Cerro Tololo, Chile, and two telescopes of 1.3 and 2.4 meter aperture at the MDM Observatory located on Kitt Peak near Tucson, Arizona. The university continues to maintain small telescopes on the top floor of Angell Hall. Plans also exist for the renovation of the University of Michigan/Detroit Observatory and its telescope.
The University of Michigan Observatory records include those of the Lamont-Hussey Observatory, the McMath-Hulbert Observatory, the Peach Mountain Observatory, the Angell Hall Laboratory, the Department of Astronomy, and records of faculty members. Documentation consists of correspondence, astronomical and meteorological observation records, financial records, reports, scrapbooks and blueprints. The collection is divided into seven series: Correspondence, Observatories, Department of Astronomy, Scrapbooks and Clippings, Observation Charts and Notebooks, Photographs, and Blueprints.
Subjects:
Angell Hall (University of Michigan); Astronomical observatories.; Astronomy.; Double stars.; Lamont-Hussey Observatory (University of Michigan); McMath-Hulbert Observatory (University of Michigan); Portage Lake Observatory (University of Michigan); Sunspots.; Telescopes.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Astronomy.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Climate.; Scrapbooks.; Detroit Observatory.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Astronomical observatories.; Brünnow, F. (Franz), 1821-1891.; Curtis, Heber Doust, 1872-1942.; Curtiss, Ralph Hamilton, 1880-1929.; Dodson, Helen Walter, 1905-; Goldberg, Leo.; Hall, Asaph, 1859-1930.; Hulbert, Henry Schoolcraft, 1869-1959.; Lamont, Robert Patterson, 1867-1948.; Lamont-Hussey Observatory (University of Michigan); McMath, Robert R. (Robert Raynolds), 1891-1962.; McMath-Hulbert Observatory (University of Michigan); Peach Mountain Radio Astronomy Observatory (Mich.); Portage Lake Observatory (University of Michigan); Telescopes.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Astronomy.; University of Michigan. Observatory.; Detroit Observatory.
Contributors:
Curtis, Heber Doust, 1872-1942.; Curtiss, Ralph Hamilton, 1880-1929.; Goldberg, Leo.; Hall, Asaph, 1859-1930.; Harrington, Mark Walrod, 1848-1926.; Hussey, William Joseph, 1862-1926.; Lamont, Robert Patterson, 1867-1948.; McLaughlin, Dean B. (Dean Benjamin), 1901-1965.; McMath, Robert R. (Robert Raynolds), 1891-1962.; Mohler, Orren, 1908-; Maxwell, Allen Douglas.; Robbins, Frank Egleston, 1884-; Rossiter, Richard Alfred, d. 1977.; Rufus, Will Carl, 1876-1946.; Shaeberle, John Martin.; Shapley, Harlow, 1885-1972.; Townley, Sidney D. (Sidney Dean), 1867-1946; Woodard, C. S. (Charles Sherman)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Architectural drawings.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (1899-1977; 2.5 linear ft.) includes correspondence of observatory directors William J. Hussey, Ralph H. Curtiss, Heber D. Curtis, W. Carl Rufus, A.D. Maxwell, Leo Goldberg, Robert R. McMath, and R.A. Rossiter. Correspondents include Robert P. Lamont, Harlow Shapley, and Frank E. Robbins.
  The Observatories series (1892-1985; 4.7 linear ft) is divided into five alphabetically arranged sub-series, representing the separate observatories operated by or affiliated with the university. Researchers should note that there is some overlap among the observatories within each of the sub-series.
  - 1889, 1904-1905 (Box 1)
  - 1906 (Box 1)
  - 1907 (Box 1)
  - 1908 (Box 1)
  - 1909, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1910, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1911, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1912, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1913, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1914 (Box 1)
  - 1915 (Box 1)
  - 1916 (Box 1)
  - 1917 (Box 1)
  - 1918 (Box 1)
  - 1919 (Box 1)
  - 1920 (Box 1)
  - 1921 (Box 1)
  - 1922, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1923, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1924, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - January 1925 (re: Eclipse of 1925) (Box 1)
  - 1925, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1926, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - 1927
    - January-April, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - May-December, 8 folders (Box 2)
  - 1928, 12 folders (Box 2)
  - 1929, 12 folders (Box 2)
  - 1930, 8 folders (Box 2)
  - 1931, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1932, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1933, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1934, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1935, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1936 (Box 2)
  - 1937, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1938 (Box 3)
  - 1939 (Box 3)
  - 1940 (Box 3)
  - 1941, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1942 (Box 3)
  - 1943 (Box 3)
  - 1944, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1945, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - 1946, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - 1947-1948 (Box 3)
  - 1949-1950 (Box 3)
  - 1949 (honoring Henry S. Hulbert) (Box 3)
  - 1951 (Box 3)
  - 1952 (Box 3)
  - 1953 (Box 3)
  - 1954-1956 (Box 3)
  - 1957-1958 (Box 3)
  - 1959 (Box 3)
  - 1960 (Box 3)
  - 1962-1965 (re: death of Robert R. McMath) (Box 3)
  - 1973-1977 (Box 3)
- Observatories
  - Angell Hall Laboratory (Ann Arbor, Michigan)
    The Angell Hall Laboratory sub-series (1925-1927, and undated) documents the laboratory and students' observatory of the Department of Astronomy located on the fifth floor and roof of Angell Hall. The sub-series includes information on equipment and facility use.
    - Miscellanea 1925-1927, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Detroit Observatory, (Ann Arbor, Michigan)
    [later University of Michigan Observatory]
    The Detroit Observatory sub-series (1892-1944) documents the University of Michigan's first observatory, located in Ann Arbor, Michigan, whose name was changed to the University of Michigan Observatory in 1931. It includes materials documenting the observatory grounds and equipment, as well as notes and writings of staff members. Also included in this subseries is a log book, prepared by consultant Christopher Ray documenting the 1997 restoration of the 1856 Fitz 12-inch refractor
    - Building and Grounds 1928-1942, undated (Box 3)
    - Inventories 1908-1926 (Box 3)
    - Personnel 1927 1 1931 undated (Box 3)
    - Budget 1939-1940 (Box 3)
    - Account Book of Meteorological Fund, Shop Fund, and Lamont House
      - 1912-1930 (Box 3)
      - 1930-1944 (Box 3)
    - Mailing List 1924 (Box 4)
    - Writings on Double Stars, R.H. Curtis (Box 4)
    - Observations and miscellaneous writings undated (Box 4)
    - "Descriptive Astronomy," Manuscript of four chapters, ca. 1924-1935 (Box 4)
    - "Latitude of the Detroit Observatory," by Ludovic Estes 1887 (Box 4)
    - Notes on testing of New Telescope (R.H. Curtis) 1907 (Box 4)
    - Sunspot Observations 1892-1895 C.S. Woodard (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Lectures, ca. 1916-1921 (Box 4)
    - Henry Draper Fund correspondence 1925-1929 (Box 4)
    - Miscellanea 1907-1948 (Box 4)
    - Logbook on restoration of Fitz 1856 12-inch refracting telescope, by Christopher Ray, 1997 (Box 4)
  - Lamont-Hussey Observatory (Bloemfontein, South Africa)
    The Lamont-Hussey Observatory sub-series (1918-1963) documents the university observatory located in South Africa. It includes correspondence and observations of observatory director R.H. Curtiss.
    - Correspondence
      - 1918-1924 (Box 4)
      - 1925-1926 (Box 4)
      - 1927, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1928, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1929 (Box 4)
      - 1930 (Box 4)
      - 1931-1932 (Box 4)
      - 1933-1935 (Box 4)
      - 1936-1938 (Box 4)
      - 1939-1944 (Box 4)
      - 1945-1948 (Box 4)
      - 1949-1954 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, R.A. Rossiter to R.H. Curtiss
      - 1926-1927 (Box 4)
      - 1928 (Box 4)
      - 1929 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, R.H. Curtiss to R.A. Rossiter
      - 1926 (Box 4)
      - 1927 (Box 4)
      - 1928 (Box 4)
      - 1929 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, R.P. Lamont
      - 1926 (Box 4)
      - 1927 (Box 4)
      - 1928 (Box 4)
      - 1929-1930 (Box 4)
    - History and Development, ca. 1924-1928, 1977, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Accounts 1938-1953 (Box 4)
    - Construction of Lamont Telescope 1910-1926 (Box 4)
    - Lamont Fund 1910-1928 (Box 4)
    - Report of W.J. Hussey's South African Trip 1924 (Box 5)
    - Double Star Observation Notes, ca. 1924-1936 (Box 5)
    - Astronomical Newsletter, ca. 1942-1946 (Box 5)
    - Miscellanea, 1 1928 undated (Box 5)
    - Spectrograph 1963 (Box 5)
  - McMath-Hulbert Observatory, (Lake Angelus, Michigan)
    The McMath-Hulbert Observatory sub-series (1937-1985) documents the university observatory located in Portage Lake, Michigan. It includes the files of Orren Mohler, director of the observatory until its closing in 1979. This sub-series also includes materials accessioned in 1980, which are located separately in box 15.
    - Floor Plans undated (Box 5)
    - Lake Angelus Support Fund
      - 1941 (Box 5)
      - 1942 (Box 5)
      - 1943 (Box 5)
      - 1944 (Box 5)
      - 1945 (Box 5)
      - 1946-1947 (Box 5)
    - McGregor Fund 1937-1950 (Box 5)
    - Miscellanea, 1 1971 undated (Box 5)
    - Orren Mohler Files
      - American Astronomical Society
        - Meeting (1963 Fairbanks), Notes on Lecture by W.M.A. Fowler on Henry Norris Russel 1963 (Box 5)
        - Nominating Committee 1962-1966 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence
        - Albion College (G.B. Carson, John A. Williams) 1972 (Box 5)
        - McMath-Hulbert Observatory (MCMHO) Corporation 1979-1980 (Box 5)
        - Miscellaneous 1980-1985 (Box 5)
        - Oakland University Appointment 1980 (Box 5)
        - Father Richard A. Miller 1959-1970 (Box 5)
        - Walter E. Mitchell, Jr. 1962-1970 (Box 5)
        - Dr. John Swenson 1962-1970 (Box 5)
      - Course Materials
        - Astronomy 121, 152, Spectroscopy Lab 1953-1968 (Box 5)
        - Astronomy 403
          - Fall 1972 (Box 5)
          - Fall 1973 (Box 5)
          - Fall 1977, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Astronomy 404 (Box 6)
          - Winter 1973 (Box 6)
          - Winter 1974 (Box 6)
          - 1975-1976, 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Miscellaneous undated (Box 6)
        - Student Papers 1974-1975 (Box 6)
      - Dome Proposals, Observadome 1968 (Box 6)
      - The 11 Largest Sunspot Groups undated (Box 6)
      - Equipment Proposals 1965 (Box 6)
      - Fulbright Materials 1960-1961 (Box 6)
      - Hoc Filter 1972-1973 (Box 6)
      - International Astronomical Union
        - Commission Membership 1963-1970 (Box 6)
        - General Assemblies 1964-1967 (Box 6)
        - Symposia 1964-1967 (Box 6)
      - McGregor Disk, ca. 1960 (Box 6)
      - McGregor Fund, Application for Telescope Funds 1967 (Box 6)
      - Mount Haleakala (Hawaii) 1969 (Box 6)
      - Neighborhood Meeting, Bloomington (Indiana) May 1, 1965 (Box 6)
      - Observations
        - He 10830
          - Analytic Tables undated (Box 6)
          - Journal of Equivalent Widths undated (Box 6)
        - HeI 10 1830 undated (Box 6)
        - Relationships of Solar Features 1956 (Box 6)
        - Solar Observations, Solar Cycles 18, 19, 20 undated (Box 6)
      - Revision of the Ultraviolet Solar Spectrum, paper undated (Box 6)
      - Spectroscope Proposal 1969 (Box 6)
      - Telescopes
        - 50" Requests 1967 (Box 6)
        - Issues 1964-1967 (Box 6)
        - Off-Axis 50mm Maximum Diameter 1971-1973 (Box 6)
        - Proposals 1965 (Box 6)
        - Proposals 1967 (Box 6)
        - Ross-Lundin Lens 1960 (Box 6)
        - 37" and Future Needs 1947-1964 (Box 6)
    - Observing Notes, Snow Telescope and McMath-Hulbert Spectroscope September, 1965 (Box 6)
    - Observatory Publications 1930-1955, 2 volumes (Box 15)
    - Notebook of R. McMath on first years of Observatory July 1930-October 1932 (Box 15)
    - History of Observatory upon occasion of its 25th anniversary (Box 15)
    - Twenty-Fifth anniversary-related correspondence 1955 (Box 15)
    - Handbook of Practical Astronomy by W.W. Campbell (Box 15)
    - Speech by Heber D. Curtis before Katholepestemiad Club, "Venerean Voyage," 1940 (Box 15)
    - Astronomy Notes 1887 of Frank C. McMath (Box 15)
    - R.R. McMath (Medal for Merit Award) (Box 15)
    - Letters from Heber D. Curtis 1930 (Box 15)
  - Portage Lake/Peach Mountain Observatory, (Dexter, Michigan)
    The Portage Lake/Peach Mountain Observatory sub-series (1947-1971) documents the university observatory located near Dexter, Michigan. It includes materials related to construction of the facility.
    - Financing 1947-1950 (Box 6)
    - Plans (Box 6)
    - Name 1947-1948 (Box 6)
    - Construction 1948 (Box 6)
    - Dedication and Symposium 1950, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Pierce Objective 1948 (Box 6)
    - Perkin-Elmer Corp. 1947-1955 (Box 6)
    - Schmidt Telescope, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Warner and Swasey 1947-1955 (Box 7)
    - Movement of Schmidt Telescope to Cerro Tololo, Chile 1965-1971 (Box 7)
- Department of Astronomy
  The Department of Astronomy series (1908-1963; 1.2 linear ft.) documents the Department of Astronomy at the University of Michigan. The series includes budgets, regents communications, and course materials. It also includes materials written by and about faculty and students, notably the files of Dean B. McLaughlin, a professor and astronomer at the university from the 1930s to the 1960s. The Orren Mohler files in the McMath-Hulbert Observatory sub-series also include related course material. Researchers should also note the existence of a separate University of Michigan Department of Astronomy record group containing more recent departmental documentation.
  - Budget 1908-1909 through 1941-1942, 6 folders (Box 7)
  - Correspondence and reports: American Astronomical Society
    - 1919 (Box 7)
    - 1927-1933 (Box 7)
    - 119th meeting (Ann Arbor, MI) 1965 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence and reports: International Astronomical Union
    - 1920-1922 (Box 7)
    - 1961 (Box 7)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 7)
  - Course Materials
    - 1907-1927 (Box 7)
    - 1924-1929 (Box 7)
  - H.D. Curtis, Lectures on Cosmosogony 1938-1939 (Box 7)
  - Faculty Biographical (Box 7)
  - Faculty Directory 1927-1928 through 1946-1947 (Box 7)
  - Faculty Records 1941 (Box 7)
  - M.W. Harrington
    - Communication to Board of Regents (Box 7)
    - Planisphere, ca. 1900 (Box 7)
  - Mary E. Lindsey
    - Method of Clock Comparison undated (Box 7)
    - Method of Recording the Daily Weather Observations in Permanent "Meteorological Observations" Record undated (Box 7)
    - McGregor Fund 1938-1939 (Box 7)
  - Dean B. McLaughlin Files
    - Correspondence, with H.C. Urey 1954-1956 (Box 7)
    - Flying Saucers 1956-1961 (Box 7)
    - Humor, undated 1956 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 7)
    - Nova Light-Curves, post-1954 (Box 7)
    - Nova Spectra 1935-1952 (Box 7)
    - Nova Velocities 1945 (Box 7)
    - Novae, Typical Course of Development 1936-1942 (Box 7)
    - Novae, Visual Estimates 1933-1963 (Box 7)
    - Observatory History, undated 1960-1961 (Box 7)
    - Observatory Time-Line undated (Box 8)
    - Other Galaxies 1955 (Box 8)
    - Programs 1952-1964 (Box 8)
    - Spectrographic Studies of Eclipsing Binaries, a dissertation, post-1922 (Box 8)
    - Sputnik Photos 1958 (Box 8)
    - Supernova Simulation 1961 (Box 8)
    - Telescope Removal 1950-1962 (Box 8)
    - 37" Programs, Statistics, etc., undated circa 1939 (Box 8)
    - Uranography, by C.A. Young (1887), 1923 (Box 8)
    - Various Papers, undated 1961-1965 (Box 8)
  - Notes on Air Navigation, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Records
    - 1921-1923 (Box 8)
    - 1924-1927 (Box 8)
    - 1928-1931 (Box 8)
    - 1969 (Box 8)
  - The Sky, prepared by Robert Petrie, edited by Donald Ries and Aimee Lambie, 1934 (Box 8)
  - Staff Meetings 1945 (Box 8)
  - Student Records
    - Josephine A. Day 1877 (Box 8)
    - Hazel Losh and R.A. Rossiter 1919-1924 (Box 8)
- Scrapbooks and Clippings
  The Scrapbooks and Clippings series (1921-1970; .6 linear ft.) covers the years 1921-1970 and documents faculty, staff, facilities, and changes in the university's observatories and the Department of Astronomy.
  - 1921-1966 (Box 8)
  - 1938-1953 (Box 8)
  - 1953-1962 (Box 8)
  - 1962-1970 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
- Observation Charts and Notebooks
  The Observation Charts and Notebooks series (1855-1944; 6 linear ft.) includes astronomical and meteorological observations made by J.M. Shaeberle, Asaph Hall Jr., William J. Hussey, C.S. Woodard, and S.D. Townley. The series is divided in three main files: Double Star Charts, Astronomical Observation Notebooks, and Meteorological Observations.
  The Double Star Charts: Northern Hemisphere files consists of the observation notebooks of William J. Hussey which note the existence and location of double stars. Some related notebooks appear in the astronomical observation notebooks subseries and in the Lamont-Hussey Observatory subseries.
  The Astronomical Observation Notebooks consist of notebooks and journals maintained by university and non-university affiliated observers dating from 1855 to 1923. The observation volumes also contain a journal used as a letter book by Asaph Hall which include his resignation letter noting problems facing the observatory. Some volumes also comment on equipment needs.
  The Meteorological Observations consist of notebooks maintained by university and non-university affiliated observers. The notebooks, particularly those from 1908 to 1944, offer detailed daily weather data for the Ann Arbor area.
  - Double-Star Charts: Northern Hemisphere (W.J. Hussey), 11 folders (Box 9)
  - Astronomical Observation Notebooks
    - Meridian Circle Observations
      - 1855-1858 Observer unidentified, 3 volumes (Box 10)
      - 1879-1886 J.M. Shaeberle, 6 volumes (Box 10)
      - 1895-1897 Asaph Hall, 23 volumes (Box 10)
      - 1898-1903 Asaph Hall, 36 volumes (Box 11)
    - Equatorial Observations of Comets and Planets 1857-1865, 1879 (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous Notebooks, containing Corrections, Factors, Class Notes, Calculations, ca. 1879-1905, 1932-1941 (Box 12)
    - Notebooks of W.J. Hussey, containing observations of Mars, Eclipses and Aurora of the Sun, Double Stars, and Miscellaneous notes
      - 1875-1923 (Box 12)
      - 1875-1923 (Box 13)
    - Notebooks of S.D. Townley
      - 1893-1901 (Box 13)
    - Other Observers
      - Frank D. Urie 1909 (Box 13)
      - Bernard H. Dawson 1912 (Box 13)
      - James A. McLaughlin 1912 (Box 13)
      - Leroy M. Coffin 1914 (Box 13)
      - Abraham M. Elkind 1919 (Box 13)
  - Meteorological Observations
    - 1859-1861 1892-1901 1902-1980 (Box 13)
      (see also outsize material, Box 17)
    - 1908-1944, 40 volumes (Box 14)
- Photographs